A Guide to the Oron J. Hale Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Oron J. Hale Papers 1891-1991
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12800
ca. 18,000 items
Estate of Oron J. "Pat" Hale
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection is a bequest from the Estate of Oron James Hale.
Biographical Sketch
Oron James ("Pat") Hale, Corcoran Professor of History at the University of Virginia, was a member of the history department from 1929 until his retirement in 1972. He was born the second son of William Robert and Frances I. (Putnam) Hale on July 29, 1902 in Goldendale, Washington, and was called "Pat" throughout his life. He graduated cum laude, Phi Beta Kappa in 1925 from the University of Washington in Seattle and later earned an M.A. (1928) and a Ph.D. (1930) at the University of Pennsylvannia in Philadelphia.
Hale's scholarly research in Europe on diplomacy and the press was pursued in the late 1920s and early 1930s in London, Paris, Berlin, and Munich where he, together with his wife Annette Van Winkle Hale whom he had married on August 7, 1929, experienced firsthand the rise of Hitler and the advent of National Socialism that drove Europe and eventually the United States to war. Hale, commissioned in the rank of Major in 1942, served with the Intelligence Division of the War Department General Staff in Washington and in 1945, with the end of hostilities, participated in a special mission of the War Department's Historical (Shuster) Commission in Germany interrogating the surviving political and military leaders of the defeated Third Reich, including such notables as Goering, Keitel, Doenitz, Ribbentrop, Rosenberg, Ley, Jodl, and von Papen.
Hale's return to Charlottesville in 1946 as Professor of European History was short-lived. In 1950, he was back in Germany to serve first as Deputy Commissioner (to George Shuster) and then as Commissioner for Bavaria under the U.S. High Commissioner for Germany, John J. McCloy, whose task it was to phase out the U.S. military occupation as Germany moved toward the restoration of its sovereignty.
Shortly after resuming his academic career at the University of Virginia (1952), Hale became chairman of the history department (1955-1962) and was instrumental in the development of a special fellowship program and history professorship that led to the appointment of his old friend and former University of Virginia colleague, Dumas Malone to serve as the first holder of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation chair. Also during this period, Hale helped organize and establish within the Southern Historical Association, the European History Section, which he chaired in 1958-1959 and, within the American Historical Association, the Committee on War Documents which he chaired in 1957 and again in 1964 when it incorporated into the Conference Group for Central European History. A highlight of Hale's involvement with the War Documents Committee was the leadership he provided in the committee's successful effort to have millions of captured Nazi government documents, then stored in the United States, declassified and microfilmed prior to their being returned to the German Federal Republic.
After resigning the department chairmanship in 1962, Hale was appointed to the Institute for Advanced Studies at Princeton, New Jersey (1963-1964) and then served as visiting summer professor at Harvard, Duke, and the Universities of Missouri and North Carolina. In 1965, he became William W. Corcoran Professor of History at the University of Virginia where he continued his work while caring for his wife, Anne, until her death in 1968.
Hale was the author of numerous articles, commentaries, and reviews on matters of German history. He was a regular contributor to The Virginia Quarterly Review, The Journal of Modern History, The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, The Journal of Central European Affairs, The American Historical Review, and The Richmond Times-Dispatch. His books include: Germany and the Diplomatic Revolution, 1904-1906 (Awarded the "George Louis Beer" prize of the American Historical Association in 1931); Publicity and Diplomacy, 1890-1914 (1940); The Captive Press in the Third Reich (Winner of the "Polk Award" in journalism in 1964); and The Great Illusion, 1900-1914 (published as part of the William L. Langer, series, Rise of Modern Europe, 1971).
In recognition of his academic achievements and government service, Hale received the Outstanding Civilian Award from the U.S. Department of the Army, 1964; the Commander's Cross of the Order of Merit of the German Federal Republic, 1969; the Thomas Jefferson Award from the University of Virginia, 1969; an honorary Litt.D. from Hampden-Sydney College, 1958; and in 1986, a "Festschrift" of original essays published in his honor by his former graduate students.
In July 1970, Hale remarried to a long time friend, Virginia Zehmer. Despite a stroke suffered in 1973 and the implantation of a pacemaker, Hale kept busy in retirement traveling, hunting, playing golf, refurbishing ancestral gravesites, and being involved in the social activities at his residence community in Richmond. In his late years, he again devoted himself to the care of his wife, Virginia, who died in 1989--three years before he was to succumb on July 19, 1991. He is buried in the University of Virginia Cemetery in Charlottesville.
Scope and Content
The collection contains ca. 18,000 items (15 shelf feet) and consists of personal letters, office correspondence, and records relating to Hale's academic activities and associations; declassified copies of intelligence reports and data, together with routine correspondence, memoranda, and administrative documents affiliated with his government service in Germany; manuscript drafts and copies of his published writings; genealogical data; photographs (ca. 2000 items) of family members, friends, and travel scenery; and personal miscellanea.
Interesting documents within the collection groupings include: (I) Correspondence: Hale's 1945 letters to his wife reporting on the aftermath of Germany's defeat in his vivid descriptions of the devastation of cities and towns they had lived in or had visited before the war and of the suffering being experienced by their old friends and colleagues. (II) Academia: A series of "Oral History" interviews that Hale gave to Charles Moran of the University of Virginia in 1976 that focus on his academic career and his government service and that reflect on the historically dramatic events with which he was involved. (III) Government Service: Copies of the U.S. War Department 's 1945 interrogation reports of high-ranking former German officials (some 22 of whom Hale interviewed) who set forth, from their personal perspectives, fascinating accounts and analyses about the war, its conduct, Hitler's leadership, and the reasons for Germany's defeat; State (Land) Commissioner of Bavaria office documents of the period 1950-1952 that give some flavor of Hale's role in implementing the United States policy of introducing and nurturing democratic concepts among the defeated German populace. (IV) Publications: German documents that served as a basis for published articles by Hale that include a copy of an memorandum regarding the biological future of the German people written by Martin Bormann, Nazi leader and Hitler's private sectretary; a 1923 copy of a letter of admonishment to Adolf Hitler from Gottfried Feder, Nazi Party economist; and photostatic copies of Hitler's tax returns which had been maintained in the Munich Finance Office from 1925-1935 and which were later part of the documents seized by the Allies during the war. (VII) Miscellany: Anne Hale's diary of pre-war Germany in which she records the attitudes and behavior of the German people in the period of rising Nazi power; memorabilia that include copies of Nazi SS documents pertaining to some of the security measures taken to protect Hitler following the assassination attempt on his life of July 20, 1940; a copy of a 1947 letter that Rudolph Hess wrote to his sister from his jail cell; and a variety of documents and letters bearing original and facsimile signatures, including those of Hitler, Ribbentrop, Albert Einstein, and Robert Oppenheimer.
Container List
- Group I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1926-1949; (4 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1960; (1 of 4 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1960; (2-4 of 4 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1964; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1987; (7 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1991, n.d.; (5 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Selected Correspondence--Alderman, Edwin A., 1929 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Biemiller, Andrew J., 1929-1980, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Boyd, Julian and Grace, 1928-1986, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Bullack, Sarah Otis, 1927-1940, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Cadbury, George W., 1939-1990, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Carruthers, E. I., 1929 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Darden, Colgate W., 1950 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--deWitt, Thomas E. J., 1970-1990 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Donaghay, Marie, 1968, 1990 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Edgar, James H., 1967-1986, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Farnsworth, Robert, 1970-1978 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Geldard, Frank and Jeanette, 1984 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Hale, Anne, 1926-1962, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Hale, Henry E., II, 1934-1946, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Hale, Jean E., 1984-1990, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Hale, Nathan, 1981-1984 (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Hale, Peter R., 1983-1990, n.d. (Box Box 5)
  - Selected Correspondence--Halstead, Charles, 1959-1977 (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Helm, David A., 1966-1989, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Heusinger, Adolf and family, 1947-1990, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Hughes, Thomas, 1951-1989, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Keen, George, 1983-1984 (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Kennett, Lee, 1955-1971, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Kraehe, Enno E., 1979-1990 (Box Box 6)
  - Selected Correspondence--Langer, William L., 1961-1982, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Layton, Roland V., Jr., 1962-1989 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Lichtenberger, Vera, 1975-1991 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Lingelbach, William E., 1950-1952 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Loewenstein, Hubertus Prince, 1937-1958 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Malone, Dumas, 1929 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--McCloy, John J., 1951-1986 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Nelson, Kenneth R. and family, 1963-1987 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Newcomb, John L., 1932-1946 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Putnam family, 1912-1976, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Ritsch, Frederick J., Jr., 1957-1982 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Ritter, Harry, 1969-1988 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Rivlin, Alice M., 1975-1984 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Shannon, Edgar F., Jr., 1969 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Shryock, Richard H. and family, 1950-1989 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Shumate, Daniel, 1952, 1986-1990 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Shuster, George N., 1945-1952 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Snead, Rayner V., Jr., 1974-1986, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Spillner family, 1933-1949 (Box Box 7)
  - Selected Correspondence--Wilcox, Larry D., 1968-1986, n.d. (Box Box 7)
- Group II: Academia
  - American Historical Association--Bibliographical Services (Oron J. Hale, Chairman), 1966-1967 (Box Box 8)
  - American Historical Association--Committee on War Documents--Correspondence and Operational Records, ca. 1955-1981, n.d.; (1-5 of 14 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - American Historical Association--Committee on War Documents--Correspondence and Operational Records, ca. 1955-1981, n.d.; (6-14 of 14 folders) (Box Boxes 9-10)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Organization and "The First Two Years" (Oron J. Hale, Secretary-Treasurer), 1957-1960 (Box Box 11)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Records and Correspondence, 1957-1989; (3 folders) (Box Box 11)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Program Committee (Oron J. Hale, Chairman)--Correspondence and Miscellaneous Records, 1954-1956 (Box Box 11)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Program Committee (Oron J. Hale, Chairman)--Kennan Session, 1955 (Box Box 11)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Program Committee (Oron J. Hale, Chairman)--Stavrianos "Mess", 1955 (Box Box 11)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Program Committee (Oron J. Hale, Chairman)--Toynbee Session, 1955 (Box Box 11)
  - American Historical Association--Conference Group for Central European History-- Program Committee (Oron J. Hale, Chairman)--Committee Chairmanship Aftermath, 1955-1957 (Box Box 11)
  - Army, Department of--Historical Advisory Committee--Oron J. Hale Membership, 1953-1972, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--Civil-Military Relations Conference, Ohio State University, 1959 (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--Faculty Christian Conference, Montreat, North Carolina, 1950, 1957-1958 (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--George Marshall Library, Lexington, Virginia, 1975-1976 (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--Georgetown History Forum, Washington, D.C., 1975 (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--National Archives Conferences, Washington, D.C., 1968-1971 (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--Research Conference, University of Kentucky, 1959 (Box Box 12)
  - Conferences (Oron J. Hale Participation)--Truman Library Conference, Independence, Missouri, 1970 (Box Box 12)
  - Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, 1962-1980, n.d. (Box Box 12)
  - Southern Historical Association, European History Section--Meeting Reports and Miscellaneous Records, 1949, 1954-1973; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Abernathy Retirement Dinner, 1961 (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Assembly of Professors--Darden Appointment and Resignation, 1947, 1959 (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Book and Authors Club, 1983 (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Centennial Committee of the Synod of Virginia, 1961 (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Contract Relations, 1946-1970 (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Corcoran Department of History--Departmental Records, 1948-1987; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Corcoran Department of History--Oron J. Hale's Chairmanship, 1955-1962, n.d. (Box Box 13)
  - University of Virginia--Deiches and Blazer Lectures (Oron J. Hale), 1953-1954 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--"Festschrift" (Oron J. Hale), 1985-1987 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Heusinger Lecture, 1961-1962 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Institute of Public Affairs, 1940-1954 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Oral History Interview of Oron J. Hale by Charles Moran--Oron J. Hale's Notes, 1976 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Phi Beta Kappa of Virginia, 1958-1979 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Retirement Letters (Oron J. Hale), 1972 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--ROTC Special Committee, 1969-1970 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Salmon Case, 1959 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Senate of the University of Virginia, 1957, 1970-1971 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--University of Virginia--Sesquicentennial Convocation Panel-- Shannon Inauguration, 1969 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Social Science Research Council Fellowship--Oron J. Hale's Notes and Interviews, 1932-1933 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Thomas Jefferson Award, 1970-1976 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Thomas Jefferson Foundation Fellowships, 1957-1960 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--Toynbee Lectures, 1957-1958 (Box Box 14)
  - University of Virginia--University Book Club, 1971-1973 (Box Box 14)
- Group III: Government Service
  - War Department General Staff, Intelligence Division--Records Pertaining to Germany's Wartime Activities, 1937-1960, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 15)
  - War Department General Staff, Intelligence Division--News Summaries of the Wartime European Press, 1943-1945; (1-6 of 8 folders) (Box Box 16)
  - War Department General Staff, Intelligence Division--News Summaries of the Wartime European Press, 1943-1945; (7-8 of 8 folders) (Box Box 17)
  - War Department, Historical (Shuster) Commision Interrogation of Former German Officials--Correspondence, Interview Notes, and Report Drafts [Interrogatee index in folders], 1945; (1-3 of 8 folders) (Box Box 17)
  - War Department, Historical (Shuster) Commission Interrogation of Former German Officials--Correspondence, Interview Notes, and Report Drafts [Interrogatee index in folders], 1945; (4-8 of 8 folders) (Box Box 18)
  - War Department, Historical (Shuster) Commission Interrogation of Former German Officials--Interrogation Reports Pertaining to Germany's Military, Political, Social, Economic, and Press Activities. Includes Oron J. Hale's "Final Report," December 20, 1945 [Interrogatee index in folders], (2 folders) (Box Box 19)
  - --U.S. High Commission for Germany--Office of the State (Land) Commissioner for Bavaria--Oron J. Hale's Office and Personal File Records, 1950-1952; (1-2 of 10 folders) (Box Box 19)
  - U.S. High Commission for Germany--Office of the State (Land) Commissioner for Bavaria--Oron J. Hale's Office and Personal File Records, 1950-1952; (3-6 of 10 folders) (Box Box 20)
  - U.S. High Commission for Germany--Office of the State (Land) Commissioner for Bavaria--Oron J. Hale's Office and Personal File Records, 1950-1952; (7-10 of 10 folders) (Box Box 21)
  - U.S. High Commission for Germany--Oron J. Hale's Media Presentations and Interviews, 1950-1952; (2 folders) (Box Box 22)
  - U.S. High Commission for Germany--Oron J. Hale's Cultural and Social Activities, 1950-1952, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 22)
- Group IV: Publications
  - Correspondence with Publishers, 1962-1980; (2 folders) (Box Box 23)
  - Writings--Manuscript Drafts and Background (Oron J. Hale), 1928-1964, n.d.; (1-4 of 7 folders) (Box Box 23)
    Includes Sicherung der Zukunft des Deutschen Volkes, by Martin Bormann.
  - Writings--Manuscript Drafts and Background (Oron J. Hale), 1928-1964, n.d.; (5-7 of 7 folders) (Box Box 24)
  - Writings--Articles and Book Reviews (Oron J. Hale), 1929,1935-1979, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 24)
  - Writings--Miscellaneous, 1930-1984, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 25)
  - Writings--Reviews and Correspondence (Oron J. Hale's Publications), 1932-1971 (Box Box 25)
  - Writings--Offprints (Oron J. Hale), 1932-1972 (Box Box 25)
- Group V: Genealogy
  - Hale Family History--Missouri, 1822-1939, n.d. (Box Box 26)
  - Hale Family History--Ancestral Records, 1891-1988, n.d. (Box Box 26)
  - Hale Family History--Washington State, 1930s-1986, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 26)
  - Hale Family History--Glastonbury, Connecticut, 1935-1990, n.d. (Box Box 26)
  - Refurbishment of Ancestral Gravesites, 1979-1990, n.d. (Box Box 26)
- Group VI: Photographs
  - Early Years, 1800s-1940s; (4 folders) (Box Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1990, n.d.; (1-2 of 4 folders) (Box Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1990, n.d.; (3-4 of 4 folders) (Box Box 28)
  - Land Commissioner (Bavaria) Period, 1950-1952; (1-3 of 6 folders) (Box Box 28)
  - Land Commissioner (Bavaria) Period, 1950-1952; (4-6 of 6 folders) (Box Box 29)
  - Academic Career Period, 1953-1970; (2 folders) (Box Box 29)
  - Senior Retirement Years, 1970s-1990; (4 folders) (Box Box 30)
- Group VII: Miscellany
  - Awards, 1952-1972; (3 folders) (Box Box 31)
  - Memorabilia--(Oron J. Hale), 1927-1962, 1980, n.d. (Box Box 32)
  - Memorabilia--(Anne Hale), 1932-1933, 1950, n.d. (Box Box 32)
  - Memorabilia--(Virginia Hale), ca. 1970s, n.d. (Box Box 32)
  - Newsclippings, 1929-1984, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 32)
  - Personal Records--Academic (Oron J. Hale, Anne Hale), 1915-1930 (Box Box 32)
  - Personal Records--Date Books (Oron J. Hale), 1931-1985 (Box Box 33)
  - Personal Records--Diary (Anne Hale), 1932-1933 (Box Box 34)
  - Personal Records--Guest Log, 1950-1969 (Box Box 34)
  - Personal Records--Military Service Records (Oron J. Hale), 1942-1962, n.d. (Box Box 34)
  - Personal Records--Miscellaneous, 1935, 1970s-1980s; (1 of 3 folders) (Box Box 34)
  - Personal Records--Miscellaneous, 1935, 1970s-1980s; (2-3 of 3 folders) (Box Box 35)
  - Personal Records--Professional, Social, and Recreational Activities, 1970s-1980s, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 35)